Charles Jesse Jones collection, 1872-1990 (bulk 1872-1936)
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections
Charles Jesse Jones collection, 1872-1990 (bulk 1872-1936)
MS 363
University of Arizona.; Guidon Books; The Finney County Kansas Historical Society
This collection consists of correspondence, photographs, publications, and articles detailing the life of quintessential pioneer cowboy Charles Jesse "Buffalo" Jones.
.6 linear feet
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections University of Arizona PO Box 210055 Tucson, AZ 85721-0055 Phone: 520-621-6423 Fax: 520-621-9733 URL: http://speccoll.library.arizona.edu/
Restrictions
None.
Biographical Note
Charles Jesse Jones, known as "Buffalo" Jones, born January 31, 1844 in Tazewell County, Illinois to Noah and Jane Jones, lead the life of the quintessential pioneer cowboy. From his early childhood in Illinois where his father once hired Attorney Abraham Lincoln, to his experience as a buffalo hunter on the Great Plains in the 1870's, and later his friendship and rivalry with Theodore Roosevelt, Jones' life story serves as an allegory for the experience of American expansionism on the western frontier. Charles J. Jones' unique role in this westward movement was his effort to save the American Bison from extinction, and subsequently to hybridize them with domestic cattle.
His early experience as a buffalo hunter lead Jones to respect the rugged, adaptive qualities of bison, simultaneously lamenting their demise and his own role in their slaughter. In the process of trying to save the bison from extinction Jones became famous for the live capture of wild animals. His reputation lead him on a series of adventures including the live capture African big game, which was filmed with both still and moving photography; the live capture of the arctic musk ox, and the capture and "spanking" of bears in Yellowstone National Park after being appointed Park Warden by President Theodore Roosevelt. The writer Zane Grey, who became friends with Jones and had accompanied him on mountain lion captures, acknowledged that Jones was the inspiration for many of his fictional characters, as well as the subject of two non fiction books, The Last of the Plainsmen, 1911 and Roping Lions in the Grand Canyon, 1924.
Charles J. Jones married Martha J. Walton (a descendent of naturalist, Isaac Walton) on January 20, 1869. They had four children, two boys died in childhood. Throughout his life Jones maintained close correspondence with his daughters, Jessie and Olive. Suffering from a chronic illness contracted while in Africa, Jones died at his daughter Olive's house in Topeka, Kansas on March 18, 1919. He is buried alongside his wife Martha and their two sons in the Valley View Cemetery, Garden City, Kansas.
Organization
The collection has been organized into the following subgroups:
Subgroup 1: Papers, 1881-1928
Subgroup 2: Photographs, ca.1872-1916
Subgroup 3: Scrapbook, 1890-1979
Scope and Content Note
The collection is contained in one manuscript box and one scrapbook.
The correspondence is mostly between family members from 1907 to 1928. The bulk of the correspondence is between C. J. Jones and his youngest daughter Olive Jones Whitmer. There is also correspondence between Olive Jones Whitmer and other family members as well as business partners of her father. There is some correspondence between C. J. Jones and business partners and others interested in his business ventures including, James Wilson, United States Secretary of Agriculture; John A. Dix, Governor of New York; and Charles Goodnight, livestock breeder.
The publications are mostly articles regarding C. J. Jones (often photocopies); broadsides and other advertising publications, some original copies; an old Yellowstone National Park brochure; an original copy of the American Bison Society Report, 1924-1926, and a dinner program for Canadian Camp, New York, 1911.
The financial and biographical records in this collection are limited to three stock certificates and a photocopy of Jones' death certificate. The scrapbook is comprised of photographic images from magazines and photocopies of articles regarding C. J. Jones' various activities.
The collection is an interesting glimpse into the personal life of C. J. Jones and his relationship with family members, and to a lesser degree his business and professional interactions.
Access Terms
Jones, Charles Jesse, 1844-1919.
Whitmer, Olive Jones.
American Bison Society.
Buffalo Jones Catalo Company.
American bison.
American bison -- Hybridization.
Bison farming -- Experiments.
Container List
- Subgroup 1: Papers, 1881-1928 (Bulk)
  - Series 1: Correspondence, 1904-1928
    Description:
    Correspondence of Charles Jesse Jones and family, 1904 1928. Also correspondence with James Wilson, U.S. Secretary of Agriculture; New York Governor John A. Dix; Lina Elise (Mrs. Zane) Grey; as well as business related correspondence.
    Arrangement:
    By family, then general; thereafter, chronological.
    - Subseries: Correspondence, family. 1904-1917
      - 48 letters from C. J. Jones to Olive Jones Whitmer, 1904-1917 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Subseries: Correspondence from C. J. Jones to Martha "Mattie" Walton Jones (wife), ca.1907
      - New York, January 21,1907 (Box 1, Folder 2)
      - New York, January 10, ca.1907 (Box 1, Folder 2)
      - Salt Lake City, June 24, 1907 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Subseries: Correspondence from C. J. Jones to Jessie Phillips Jones: 1910-1914
      - October 25, 1910 (Box 1, Folder 2)
      - July 28, 1911 (Box 1, Folder 2)
      - February 24, 1914 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Subseries: Correspondence, family, general, 1906-1936
      - Draft of legal agreement of Buffalo Jones Catalo Co. by C.J Jones and Martha J. Jones, September 16, 1906 (Box 1, Folder 3)
      - To Mrs.Whitmer, from J. F. Jones [business partner of C. J. Jones?], September 18, 1914 (Box 1, Folder 3)
      - Aunt K. to Jessie P. Jones, 1936 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Subseries: Correspondence of Olive Jones Whitmer, ca.1911-1928
      - From J. F. Jones, November 19, 1911, March 28, 1914 (Box 1, Folder 3)
      - From J. F. Jones, September 17, 1914 (Box 1, Folder 3)
      - From J. F. Jones, January 22, 1916 (Box 1, Folder 3)
      - From Lina Elise (Mrs. Zane) Grey, March 21, 1919 (Box 1, Folder 3)
      - From Lenox Curtis of Canadian Camp, April 5, 1923 (Box 1, Folder 3)
      - From J. D. Hand, February 4, 1927 (Box 1, Folder 3)
      - Eight letters from Jim Owens (Uncle?) to Jessie Jones Phillips(?), 1923-1928 (Box 1, Folder 3)
      - From "Katie" (sister) to C.J. Jones (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Subseries: Correspondence, photocopies of originals in folder 5, 1908-1918
      - [same as folder 5] (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Subseries: Correspondence, originals [fragile], 1908-1918
      - From C. J. Jones to James Wilson, Secretary of Agriculture, Washington, D.C., regarding hybridized sheep and cattle, Fredonia, AZ. [6 pages], January 27, 1908 (Box 1, Folder 5)
      - Letter to C. J. Jones from The American Bison Society President Edmund Seymour [2 pages], September 18, 1917 (Box 1, Folder 5)
      - Letter to C. J. Jones from The American Bison Society Secretary M. S. Garretson [2 pages], January 19, 1918 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Subseries: Correspondence, general. C. J. Jones, 1907-1917
      - From Frank Onstatt and James T. Owens (2) handwritten copies (written draft and final copy) recounting Zane Grey's Grand Canyon trip with C. J. Jones, Fredonia, AZ., 1907 (Box 1, Folder 6)
      - From New York Governor John A, Dix, April 18, 1911 (Box 1, Folder 6)
      - From C. J. Jones in France, April 1, 1914 (Box 1, Folder 6)
      - From C. J. Jones [London], 1914 (Box 1, Folder 6)
      - C. J. Jones, London (to whom?), September 20, 1914 (Box 1, Folder 6)
      - From C. J. Jones(?) to James Coddington, September 5, 1916 (Box 1, Folder 6)
      - From "Buffalo" Jones to Progressive Party, October 25, 1916 (Box 1, Folder 6)
      - From Jim Owens, January 7, 1917 (Box 1, Folder 6)
      - From C.T. Jones to Edmund Seymour, San Antonio, April 1, 1917 (Box 1, Folder 6)
      - From C. Goodnight to C.T. Jones, Goodnight, Texas, April 9, 1917 (Box 1, Folder 6)
      - From C.T. Jones to C. Goodnight, San Antonio, April 16, 1917 (Box 1, Folder 6)
      - From J. F. Jones to Col. Jones, September 5, 1917 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Series 2: Publications, 1901-1990
    Includes articles about C. J. Jones, flyers regarding various events, advertising brochures, promotional materials for Jones' financial activities, and American Bison Society publications 1912, 1924 and 1926.
    - Subseries: Publications, ca.1901-1926
      - Report of the American Bison Society [in envelope], 1924-1926 (Box 1, Folder 7)
      - Denver Post advertisement regarding "Buffalo," (Box 1, Folder 7)
      - Jones show [2 photocopies], 1916 (Box 1, Folder 7)
      - Glacier National Park brochure (Box 1, Folder 7)
      - Kansas City Times article [photocopy], October 7, 1919 (Box 1, Folder 7)
      - Lecture bulletin for "Buffalo" Jones, 1907 (Box 1, Folder 7)
      - Article The Real Conquest of the West, 1907 (Box 1, Folder 7)
      - C. J. Jones article The Capture of Mountain Sheep[photocopy], ca.1901 (Box 1, Folder 7)
      - Advertising bulletin proof page (Box 1, Folder 7)
      - Advertising bulletin for "Buffalo" Jones film of live animal captures in Africa, ca.1916 (Box 1, Folder 7)
      - Book excerpt from Charles Goodnight: cowman and plainsman by J. Evetts Haley, page 453 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Subseries: Publications, ca.1911-1990
      - Advertising flyers(3) for Persiarino lamb from the Buffalo Jones Hybridizing Station, Las Vegas and Portales, New Mexico (Box 1, Folder 8)
      - C. J. Jones (1) page biography from Arctic vol. 37, no. 2; June, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 8)
      - Full page magazine photo on reverse side (by Cherry Kearton), ca.191l (Box 1, Folder 8)
      - Canadian Camp Ninth Annual Dinner Announcement; drawing on cover of guest of honor, C. J. Jones, March 6, 1911 (Box 1, Folder 8)
      - American Bison Society dinner announcement at Delmonico's, February 23, 1912 (Box 1, Folder 8)
      - U.S. News and World Report, with cover photo of Buffalo Bill Cody, Pawnee Bill and Buffalo Jones, May 21, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 8)
      - Arizona Highways Magazine article about C. J. Jones, with cover photo of Buffalo Bill Cody, Pawnee Bill and Buffalo Jones, September ,1978 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Series 3: Certificates, 1905-1919
    Three Stock Certificates, 1881-1916.
    One Death Certificate, 1919.
    Chronological.
    - Subseries: Financial Records, 1881-1916
      - Stock certificate of The McPherson Mining and Milling Co., Colorado, in the Name of Mrs. R.Whitmer, March 1881 (Box 1, Folder 9)
      - Stock certificate of The Buffalo Jones Catalo Co. in the name of Jesse P. Jones, October 25, 1905 (Box 1, Folder 9)
      - Stock certificate of The National Irrigation and Power Company in the name of Charles R. Whitmer, 1916 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Subseries: Personal records, 1919-1958
      - Death Certificate for C. J. Jones, March 18, 1919 (Box 1, Folder 9)
      - [photocopy of death certificate] September 23, 1958 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Subgroup 2: Photographs, ca.1872-1916
  - Photographs, ca.1872 1920's
    Portraits of Charles Jones; Jesse Jones; Buffalo Bill, Pawnee Bill and Buffalo Jones together; photographs of bison herds; sheep flocks; and African animal capture. Some original photographs, some copy photographs, and some photocopies of original photographs.
    Dimension (small to large)
    - Subseries: Photographs 1872-1941
      - C. J. Jones, 1872; 4x2" New York Gallery Print, St.Joseph MO., by W.T. Duer Buffalo herd with Cowboy, on 4x5" matte board (Box 1, Folder 10)
      - Man with two "Persiarino Sheep," (Box 1, Folder 10)
      - Three tents in woods (Box 1, Folder 10)
      - C. J. Jones in Stetson hat, signed [photo from magazine] (Box 1, Folder 10)
      - Cowboy and five cattle (Box 1, Folder 10)
      - Mountain Lion on chain in barn loft. Inscription: "Captured Mountain Lion Yellowstone Park" (Box 1, Folder 10)
      - Small Buffalo herd (20) on grassland (Box 1, Folder 10)
      - C. J. Jones portrait with hat and necktie (Box 1, Folder 10)
      - Buffalo along fence in gullied area, McCook, Nebraska; inscription reads: "1881 Compliments R. E. Stotts 1941, " 1881 (Box 1, Folder 10)
      - C. J. Jones, montage of cutout photographs with inset of rhinoceros (Box 1, Folder 10)
      - Jessie Jones Phillips [center], youngest daughter of C. J. Jones, in 1920's era clothes with Chief Turtle and Chief Eagle, both in Plains Indian (Blackfeet?) headdress, "She's an Indian Princess" written on back of photo (Box 1, Folder 10)
      - Jim Owens next to a tree, "The Denver and Rio Grande Western R.R. Co." stamp on back of photograph (Box 1, Folder 10)
      - Two lambs balanced on plank (Box 1, Folder 10)
      - C. J. Jones photo, (2) signed copy photographs (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Subseries: Photograph / Postcard
      - Persiarino Sheep Postcard advertising C. J. Jones breeding business (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Subseries: Photocopies of photographs, ca.1890-1920's
      - Buffalo Bill, Pawnee Bill and Buffalo Jones; 2 different poses; 3 photocopies total (Box 1, Folder 11)
      - Jessie Jones Phillips with Chief Turtle and Chief Eagle, ca.1920's (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Subseries: Photocopies of photographs and etchings, ca.1902-1920's
      - C. J. Jones standing by irrigation flume (Box 1, Folder 11)
      - Child in stagecoach, man standing outside (Box 1, Folder 11)
      - Cowboys (3) in woods by lake (Box 1, Folder 11)
      - Pack trip w/ 15 people, trees in background (Box 1, Folder 11)
      - Cowboys in mountains taking in scenic views (Box 1, Folder 11)
      - Fred Harvey Corporation postcard of Indian farmers, [photocopy of etching] (Box 1, Folder 11)
      - Grand Canyon view [Detroit Photography Company], 1902 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Subseries: Photocopies
      - Persiarino Sheep on grassland (Box 1, Folder 11)
      - Two Buffalo in yolk pulling sled (Box 1, Folder 11)
      - Yellowstone Park stagecoach (Box 1, Folder 11)
      - Drawing of (2) Cowboys trying to lasso African lion (Box 1, Folder 11)
      - Man seated next to Gorilla (Box 1, Folder 11)
      - Three men holding Chimpanzee; [on same page] cartoon of C. J. Jones in Africa (Box 1, Folder 11)
      - Buffalo Jones Broadsides (2) advertising motion pictures of African live animal captures (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Subgroup 3: Scrapbook, 1890-1979
  Scrapbook with articles, correspondence and photographs regarding C. J. Jones activities ranging from buffalo raising; to Warden of Yellowstone; to African animal capture. Scrapbook photographs (from magazines) are thought to have been compiled by his daughter, Olive.
  - Scrapbook of C.J. Jones Activities and History, 1890-1979 (Box 2, Folder 1)